Preliminary Guide to the John S. Bradway Papers, 1922-1949
Duke University. University Archives
John S. Bradway papers 1922-1949
Duke University. University Archives
Bradway, John Saeger, 1890-1985.
60 linear feet Extent: 40,000 Items
Papers of John S. Bradway, lawyer, legal aid advocate, and educator. Bradway's primary interest and work was in the field of legal aid. He served as Secretary of the National Association of Legal Aid Organizations (NALAO) from 1922-1940, and as its President from 1940-1942. While at Duke University, Bradway founded and directed the Duke Legal Aid Clinic from 1931 until 1959. The bulk of the collection reflects Bradway's role as Secretary for the National Association of Legal Aid Organizations (NALAO). Materials include correspondence with various state and city legal aid bureaus, detailed statistics and annual reports from these organizations, correspondence with various national social service and aid agencies such as the National Conference on Social Work, and NALAO committee reports and conference proceedings. Also included are chapter files of his books, addresses, and articles written by Bradway on topics relating to legal aid.
RL.01414
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
In accordance with the Family Education Rights and Privacy Act of 1974 as amended, Duke University permits students to inspect their education records and limits the disclosure of personally identifiable information from education records.
Portions of these materials are restricted by donor request.
In off-site storage; 48 hours advance notice is required for use.
Provenance
The John S. Bradway Papers were received by the University Archives as a transfer in 1962, 1973.
Biographical Note
John S. Bradway was born Feb. 17, 1890 in Swarthmore, Pennsylvania to William and Jennie S. Bradway. He graduated from Haverford College with an A.B. in 1911 and an A.M. in 1915. He received his law degree from University of Pennsylvania in 1914 and received an honorary law degree from Haverford in 1957. Bradway began his academic teaching career at the University of Pennsylvania where he taught in the Sociology Department from 1927 to 1928. At the same time, he taught at the Pennsylvania School of Social and Health Work (1927-1929). In 1929 he moved to California and began a short career at the University of Southern California Law School (1929-1931). Bradway moved to Durham in 1931 where he taught law at Duke from 1931 to 1959. After leaving Durham, Bradway taught at the Hastings College of Law in San Francisco and at California Western University until his retirement in 1970. Bradway was married to Mary Henderson in 1921. He died on January 2, 1985 in Eureka, California.
Bradway's primary interest and work was in the field of legal aid. He served as Secretary of the National Association of Legal Aid Organizations (NALAO) from 1922-1940, and as its President from 1940-1942. While at Duke, Bradway founded and directed the Duke Legal Aid Clinic from 1931 until 1959. The purpose of the Clinic was to provide practical training for law students. They participated in practical activities such as conferring with clients, gaining interview skills, and preparing a real case for trial. Students acquired skills in legal writing through the preparation of trial briefs and legal memoranda. The Clinic served clients who were unable to pay counsel fees, most often the indigent, immigrants, minorities, and servicemen. In addition to Bradway, the Clinic had a staff of five members of the North Carolina State Bar who assisted in educational and supervisory activities, as well as representing the Clinic's clients in court. Bradway lobbied throughout his career for law schools to make a commitment for student training through legal aid clinics.
Bradway's service to the legal aid community was extensive. He chaired the legal aid committees of the Pennsylvania and North Carolina Bar Associations, as well as the Legal Aid Clinics Committee of the Association of American Law Schools. He was also an active member of the National Conference of Social Work, the American Association of Social Workers, the International Bar Association, and served as chair of the Research Committee for the Interprofessional Commission on Marriage and Divorce Laws.
His dedication to social service and legal aid extended to state and local organizations. He served as president of the North Carolina Conference for Social Service, North Carolina Mental Hygiene Society, State Legislative Council, and as director of the North Carolina League for Crippled Children. In Durham, Bradway was president of the Durham Council of Social Agencies, Family Service Agency, Rotary Club, and the Crime Study Club. He was a member of the Advisory Board of the Durham Child Guidance Clinic, Salvation Army Home and Hospital, YWCA, and Community Chest. In addition, he was chair of a committee appointed by the Durham City Council to establish a Juvenile Court in 1933, and of a committee appointed to study sub-standard housing in 1948.
Bradway wrote extensively on the topic of legal aid. His publications include:
How To Organize a Legal Aid Clinic, 1931.
Forms of Legal Aid Organizations, 1940.
Duke University Legal Aid Clinic Handbook, 1954.
The History of a Lawsuit, 1958.
How to Practice Law Effectively, 1958.
The bulk of the collection reflects the work of John S. Bradway in his role as Secretary for the National Association of Legal Aid Organizations (NALAO). Materials include correspondence with various state and city legal aid bureaus, detailed statistics and annual reports from these organizations, correspondence with various national social service and aid agencies such as the National Conference on Social Work, and NALAO committee reports and conference proceedings. Also included are chapter files of his books, addresses, and articles written by Bradway on topics relating to legal aid.
The collection is unprocessed and remains in original order as found in boxes. Red volumes are subject bound letterbooks from Bradway’s work primarily for and with the NALAO. There also appears to be two different numbered sets of Yellow volumes. One set contains NALAO material. Duke Legal Aid Clinic (DLAC) materials are also present.
Subject Headings
Bradway, John Saeger, 1890-1985; Duke University. Legal Aid Clinic; Lawyers -- United States; Legal Aid -- United States; National Association of Legal Aid Organizations
Contents of Collection
- Container List, 51 Boxes
  The bulk of the collection reflects the work of John S. Bradway in his role as Secretary for the National Association of Legal Aid Organizations (NALAO). Materials include correspondence with various state and city legal aid bureaus, detailed statistics and annual reports from these organizations, correspondence with various national social service and aid agencies such as the National Conference on Social Work, and NALAO committee reports and conference proceedings. Also included are chapter files of his books, addresses, and articles written by Bradway on topics relating to legal aid.
  The collection is unprocessed and remains in original order as found in boxes. Red volumes are subject bound letterbooks from Bradway's work primarily for and with the NALAO. There also appears to be two different numbered sets of Yellow volumes. One set contains NALAO material. Duke Legal Aid Clinic (DLAC) materials are also present.
  - Red Vol. 34, 1924-33 (Box 1)
    Philadelphia: Legal Aid Bureau, Voluntary Defenders Committee
    Buffalo Legal Aid Society
    Philadelphia Conference of Social Work
  - Red Vol. 33
    -Pennsylvania: Pottsville, Scranton, Towanda, Wilkes-Barre
    Pennsylvania Prison Society
    Rhode Island Legal Aid Society
  - Red Vol. 32
    Compis Juris of Legal Aid (outline)
    Incorporation of NALAO
    Case load questionnaire
    Treasurer's Reports, 1927-1929
    Member Reports
  - Red Vol. 36
    Correspondence with S.C., Tenn., Tex., Utah, Va., Wa., W.V., Wisc., Australia, Belgium, and the League of Nations
  - Red Vol. 23, 1923-1929 (Box 2)
    Legal Aid Society of San Francisco
    Public Defender of Los Angeles
    Legal Aid Bureau of Indiana
    Legal of Bureau of Chicago-Criminal Courts Bureau
  - Red Vol. 20, 1922-1930
    Legal Aid Society of Pittsburgh
    Public Charities Association of Pennsylvania
    Children's Bureau-Philadelphia
    Legal Aid Society of Denver
    Social Service Bureau-Pontiac, MI
  - Red Vol. 19, 1923-1930
    Family Service Society of Canton, OH
    Legal Aid Work: Columbus, Cincinnati, Cleveland, Toledo
    Correspondence, Greensboro, N.C.
  - Red Vol. 18, 1928-1933
    National Social Work Council
    Chicago University: School of Social Service Administration
    Paper: "The Purpose and Nature of Courses in Law for Social Workers"
  - Yellow Vol. 15 (Box 3)
    Miscellaneous documents relating to various NALAO committees
  - Yellow Vol. 14
    Newspapers Clippings
    Specific Legal Societies
  - Yellow Vol. 13
    N.Y. Legal Aid Societies
    Brief: Klein vs. Hultun, North Dakota Supreme Court
    Paper: "Legal Aid Work-A Social Service"
    International Legal Aid Work
    Workmen's Compensation
  - Yellow Vol. 9
    International legal aid work
  - Yellow Vol. 8
    Papers and Speeches
  - Yellow Vol. 7
    Committee on the Public Defender
  - Yellow Vol. 26, 1930-1931 (Box 4)
    Figures of Legal Aid Organizations
  - Yellow Vol. 25, 1929-1930
  - Yellow Vol. 23
    Biographical material on heads of NALAO member organizations (includes photographs)
  - Yellow Vol. 22
  - Yellow Vol. 28
    Figures of Legal Aid Organizations, 1932-1933
  - Yellow Vol. 27
    Figures of Legal Aid Organizations, 1931-1932
  - Yellow Vol. 19
    Figures of Legal Aid Organizations, 1927
  - Yellow Vol. 18
    NALAO Papers by the Secretary
    Miscellaneous Reports
  - Yellow Vol. 6 (Box 5)
    Ellis Estate: Reports of Similar Cases
    NALAO Miscellaneous Committees
    Relations with the Bar
    Small Loans
    Committee on Wage Claims
  - Yellow Vol. 5
    Ellis Estate: Material Relating to Waiting Lists
    NALAO: Early Work of the Committee on Records, on Relations with Social Agencies and on Domestic Relations Courts, 1923-1924
  - Yellow Vol. 4
    Legal aid matters leading to the establishment of the NALAO on June 7, 1923
  - Yellow Vol. 3
    Legal aid material indicating work of Secretary, June-August, 1922
    Ellis Estate: Miscellaneous Data Collected
  - Red Vol. 3, 1922-1930 (Box 6)
    Legal Aid Work of Clinic at Univ. of Southern California
    Memphis Legal Aid Society
    Social Welfare League, Seattle, WA
  - Red Vol. 4, 1923-1929
    Material on International Law
    Paper: "Public Legal Aid Work"
    International Migration Service
    Paper: "Does the Law Provide Adequate Protection for Beneficiaries of Charitable Trusts?"
    Paper: "Charitable Trust of Charles E. Ellis"
  - Red Vol. 5, 1923-1930
    Parents' Council of Philadelphia
    Reading, PA Welfare Federation
    Paper on: Average Man and his Chance in our Courts
  - Yellow Vol. 29:
    NALAO Bulletins Nos. 1-38
  - Yellow Vol. 31, 1932-1934
    NALAO Committee Reports
  - Red Vol. 9, 1922-1932 (Box 7)
    Legal Aid Society, Cincinnati
    Pennsylvania Bar Association
    National Probation Association
  - Red Vol. 11, 1922-1931
    Chicago Legal Aid Society
    Handbook Correspondence
  - Red Vol. 12, 1922-1931
    Legal Aid Societies, Cleveland and Albany
    Re: Legal Aid Work for Chinese
    Reports
  - Red Vol. 13, 1922-1929
    Paper: "Co-operation of Legal Aid Societies and labor Commission in the Collection of Unpaid Wages"
    Minimum Statistics
    Legal Aid Society of N.Y.C.
  - Red Vol. 35, 1922-1933 (Box 8)
    Legal Aid Bureau of the Educational Alliance of N.Y.
    National Desertion Bureau
    N.Y. Legal Aid Society
    N.Y. Section of the National Council of Jewish Women
  - Red Vol. 38, 1922-1933
    Correspondence, N.J., Neb., N.Y. Legal Aid Society, N.Y. Voluntary Defenders Committee
  - Red Vol. 39, 1922-1933
    Correspondence, Legal Aid Societies in Mich., Minn., Miss., Missouri, Mont.
  - Red Vol. 40, 1929-1931
    NALAO Committees
    NALAO Executive Committee
    National Handbook
    Committee on Domestic Relations Courts
  - Red Vol. 45, 1924-1933
    Correspondence, Stockholm, India, Milwaukee, England, Honolulu, and Manila
  - Red Vol. 6, 1925-1931 (Box 9)
    Collections Judgements
    Welfare Federation of Cleveland
    Conciliation Courts
    Boston Legal Aid Society-Workmen's Compensation
  - Red Vol. 7, 1925-1932
    National Conference of Social Work
    American Bar Association
    Correspondence with Alice Waldo
    Paper: "Legal-social Investigation"
    Child Welfare League of America
  - Red Vol. 8, 1928-1932
    Draft of Handbook of Legal Aid Work
    Books and Articles on Legal Aid Work
  - Red Vol. 10, 1923-1931
    White House Conference on Child Health and Protection
    Papers: "Arbitration of Small Claims as a Relief for Court Congestion"; "The Massachusetts Workmen's Compensation Act in Action"
  - Red Vol. 41, 1922-1933 (Box 10)
    Correspondence with Reginald Smith
    Harvard Legal Aid Bureau
    Boston Legal Aid Society
    Correspondence, Mass. and Mich.
  - Red Vol. 42, 1924-1933
    Interracial Commission
    N.C. Bar Association
    General N.C. Correspondence
    General Correspondence, Ohio, Okla., N.D., Ore., Cincinnati, Dayton, Cleveland
  - Red Vol. 43, 1929-1931
    Auto chattel foreclosure
    International Legal Aid Committee
  - Red Vol. 44, 1929-1933
    NALAO Financial material
    Child Welfare League
  - Red Vol. 46, 1930-1933
    Treasurer's Report
    Brief on Question: "Are Legal Aid Societies Engaged in Unlawful Practice of the Law?"
  - Red Vol. 21, 1922-1929 (Box 11)
    Dept. of Public Welfare-Bureau of Legal Aid, Philadelphia
    Correspondence with Roman Hassrick; The Annals
    Voluntary Defenders Committee
    Paper: "Desirability of a Public Defender"
    Address: "Progress of Legal Aid Work in Pennsylvania"
    Paper: "Legal Aid and Its Proper Relation to Members of the Bar"
  - Red Vol. 30, 1929-1931
    Pennsylvania Legal Aid Organizations
    National Conference on Social Work
    Correspondence with Justin Miller concerning establishment of Legal Aid Clinic at Duke, 1930-1931
    Legal Aid Society of Cincinnati
  - Red Vol. 31, 1927-1933
    American Association for Labor Legislation
    American Social Hygiene Association
    Foreign Language Information Service
    Family Welfare Association
    National Crime Commission
  - Red Vol. 37, 1923-1931
    NALAO Financial Material
    NALAO Committee on Records
    Biographical Material on Members
  - Red Vol. 47, 1928-1932 (Box 12)
    Correspondence re: Bulletins
    Functions of Legal Aid Societies
    Suggested outline of case studies book
    Series of Papers read by Bradway-Report from United States to League of Nations: "Questions Relating to Legal Aid for the Poor", 1924 (prepared by NALAO)
    "Footprints" -news clipping notebook on establishment of Duke Legal Aid Clinic
  - Red Vol. 48, 1928-1932
    W. Bruce Coble
    National Symbol
  - Red Vol. 49, 1930-1933
    Financial Problems
    Detailed Statistics
    Complaints
    Biographical Material
  - Red Vol. 14, 1922-1931 (Box 13)
    American Institute of Criminal Law and Criminology
    Phi Delta Phi
    Bradway Paper: "Legal Internship"
    Paper: "Unemployment as seen by Legal Aid Societies"
    Address: "The Prisoner at the Bar"
    Correspondence concerning Annals
    Paper: "Case of the Dead Hand"
    Correspondence with the Legal Aid Dept. of the Jewish Social Service Bureau of Chicago
  - Red Vol. 15, 1922-1931
    League of Nations, 1925
    Material on Political Science Course
    Outline of textbook for Law Students in Legal Clinics
    Southern California Legal Aid Clinic Association
    Small Loan law
    Loan Sharks
  - Red Vol. 16, 1922-1929
    Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1923
    Correspondence with Laura Spelman Rockefeller Assocation
    New NALAO Constitution, 1925-1928
    Paper: "An Analysis of the Legal Cases of The International Migration Service"
    Draft of Report of Joint Committee on Domestic Relations Court
    League of Nations, International Arrangements for Legal Assistance for the Poor
    Paper: "Legal Aid Statistics and What they Show"
  - Red Vol. 17, 1927-1931
    Preliminary notes and materials in preparation for book Bar and Public Relations
  - Red Vol. 22, 1922-1930 (Box 14)
    U.S. Dept. of Labor
    Children's Bureau
    Bureau of Labor Statistics
    Establishment of Legal Aid Organization in Washington
    Correspondence with W.H. Taft
    Family Welfare Assoc. of N.Y.C.
    Voluntary Defenders Committee of the Legal Aid Society
  - Red Vol. 24, 1922-1930
    Handbook of Legal Aid Work
    Legal Aid Newsletter and Misc. Correspondence
    Legal Aid Society of Rhode Island
    Creation of Newport, R.I. Legal Aid Council
    Russel Sage Foundation
    Charity Organization Society of Yonkers, N.Y.
  - Red Vol. 27, 1923-1931
    Correspondence with Carl Wheaton
    Preliminary draft of Committee on Curriculum
    Memo to Dean Hale-Univ. of Southern California
    General Correspondence with Univ. of Southern California faculty
  - Red Vol. 28, 1922-1929
    Courts Committee of Brooklyn Bureau of Charity
    Welfare Council of N.Y.C.
    Louis Fabricant
    Legal Aid Bureau of Buffalo
    Paper: "Legal Aid in Richmond"
  - Requests, 1939-1940 (Box 15)
  - Re: Statistics, 1940
  - Los Angeles Legal Aid Clinic, 1929-32
  - Los Angeles, 1931-1932
  - Los Angeles, 1932
  - Glendale, CA, 1932
  - Canada, 1930-1931
  - Toronto, 1929-1932
  - Montreal, 1923-1925
  - Winnipeg, 1924-1932
  - Denver, 1930-1933
  - San Diego, 1931
  - Southern California Legal Aid Clinic, 1932
  - California-General, 1931
  - Denver, 1927-1930
  - Oakland, 1923-1933
  - California-General, 1932
  - National Conference on Family Relations, 1947
  - William M. Ottinger, 1929-1933 (Box 16)
  - American Association of Social Workers, 1935
  - National Conference of Social Work, 1934-1935
  - American Bar Association, 1937
  - NALAO 1938 Conference
  - Legal Aid Committee-Bridgeport, CT
  - Hartford, CT, 1923-1933
  - New Haven, CT, 1930
  - Yale Law School, 1924-1929
  - Connecticut, 1930
  - Legal Aid Society-Washington, D.C., 1932-1933
  - American Association of Personal Finance Companies, 1931-1933
  - Membership Applications (Box 17)
  - NALAO Committee Reports, 1937-1938
  - Inquiries, 1937-38
  - NALAO Conference, 1938
  - Proceedings of Montreal Meeting, 1938
  - Washington, D.C., 1931-1933
  - U.S. Children's Bureau, 1932-1933
  - Washington, D.C., 1931
  - Legal Aid Bureau-New Orleans, 1930-1933
  - Detailed Statistics, 1934 (Box 18)
  - "How to Organize Legal Aid Organizations"-Plans
  - Correspondence with Grace P. Manners, 1934-1935
  - NALAO Committee Reports, 1934-1935
  - American Bar Association-Legal Aid Committee, 1937-1938
  - American Association of Schools of Social Work, 1937
  - National Conference of Social Work, 1936-1937
  - Public Administration Service, 1936-1937
  - Gardiner Nominating Committee, 1934
  - NALAO Convention, 1934-1935
  - NALAO Convention Suggestions, 1935 (Box 19)
  - Pennsylvania Bar Association Legal Aid Committee, 1936-1937
  - Replies from NALAO Executive Committee, 1939-1940
  - Inquiries, 1936-1937
  - Detailed Statistics, 1931-1933
  - Chapter of "How to Organize Legal Aid Organizations"
  - National Conference of Social Work, 1945 (Box 20)
  - Pennsylvania Bar Association Committee on War Work, 1945
  - Pennsylvania Bar Association Report of Legal Committees, 1941
  - Pennsylvania Bar Association Legal Aid Committee, 1940-1941
  - NALAO-National Defense Work, 1940-1941
  - Inter-American Bar Association, 1940-1941
  - Correspondence and chapter drafts for How to Organize a Legal Aid Society. (Box 21)
  - American Bar Association, 1939-1940
  - National Social Work Council, 1939-1940
  - Junior Bar Conference, 1939-1940
  - Minimum Statistics, 1939
  - Community Chests, 1939
  - American Association of Personal Finance, 1939-1940
  - Misc. Reports, 1941 (Box 22)
  - Requests, 1940-1941
  - Russel Sage Grant, 1940-1941
  - Sectional Meeting, 1941
  - Surveys, 1940-1941
  - "A Tentative Bibliography of Legal Aid Work"
  - Correspondence with Mr. Boyce concerning Gainesville Program, 1940
  - Jacksonville Conference, 1940
  - Pennsylvania Bar Association National Defense Activities, 1940-1941
  - Committee on Law-National Conference of Social Work, 1940-1941
  - New Legal Aid Organizations, 1940-1941
  - Personal Letters, 1940-1941
  - Small claims courts
  - State Bar Committees
  - Trips
  - Committee Reports, 1940
  - Alien Registration (Box 23)
  - American Bar Association
  - National Conference on Social Work
  - NALAO Bulletin #124
  - Committee Correspondence and Reports, 1941 (Box 24)
  - Bibliography of Legal Aid Material
  - Legal Aid Bureau correspondence by State, 1935-1937
  - Miscellaneous, 1948-1949
  - National Conference on Social Work
  - Legal Service Bureau
  - Chapter Files and Materials for How to Organize a Legal Aid Society
  - Chapter Files and Materials for How to Organize a Legal Aid Society (Box 25)
  - Brief on relationship between legal aid work and the bar
  - Detailed stats, 1936
  - Committee Reports, 1939
  - Legal Aid Bureau correspondence by state: 1935-1938 (Box 26)
  - Legal Aid Bureau correspondence by state: 1935-1938 (Box 27)
  - Bound volume of "Legal Aid Review" by N.Y. Legal Aid Society. Vol. XXXIII (1935) to Vol. XXXIX (1941). Missing Vol. XXXV Nos. 1, 2, 3.
  - American Bar Association-Legal Aid Committee, 1936-1937 (Box 28)
  - Jacksonville Convention, 1940
  - Jacksonville Legal Aid Committee, 1936
  - Correspondence with Legal Aid Societies (1933-36)
  - NALAO Proceedings of Pittsburgh Meeting, 1937
  - E-F: General Correspondence, 1947
  - National Probation Association, 1945
  - NALAO convention, 1936
  - NALAO conference, 1936 (Box 29)
  - Committee reports, 1936
  - Biographical material (incl. photographs) of NALAO leaders
  - NALAO conference, 1936
  - Legal Aid correspondence by state: 1935-1939
  - Legal Aid correspondence by state: 1935-1939 (Box 30)
  - [The 3 files below belong at end of box 35]
  - Clinic Student Material
  - Chapter Files-Clinical Preparation for Law Practice
  - Correspondence, 1945-1947
  - Folders appear to contain contents of disbound letterbooks or folders (kept in page order). (Box 31)
  - Legal Aid Organizations-Annual reports, 1927-1929
  - Legal Aid Organizations-Annual Reports and Blank Forms, 1927-1931
  - Legal Aid Organizations-Blank Forms and Reports
  - Minimum Statistics, 1926
  - Legal Aid Organizations-Annual Reports and Speeches by Bradway, 1922-1927
  - Detailed Statistics, [c. 1924-1925]
  - Minimum Statistics and Reports, 1922-1929
  - Minimum Statistics and Reports, 1926-1930
  - Legal Aid Organizations-Annual Reports, 1925-1926
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1933-1937
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1933-1945
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1934-1947
  - North Carolina, Duke, and Durham material (Box 32)
  - Legal Ethics, 1932-1935 (FERPA rules apply)
  - Student Loan Fund Committee, 1933-1935
  - Library vs. Miller Motor Express, 1934
  - Student Loan Fund material
  - Medical School Lectures, 1934-1935
  - Minutes of Faculty Meetings, 1934-1935
  - Roundtable on Legal Aid Clinics, 1933-1934
  - Roundtable on Legal Aid Clinics, 1934-1935
  - Medico-Legal, 1933-1934
  - Memos to Dean Miller, 1933-1934
  - Minutes of Faculty Meetings, 1933-1934
  - Miscellaneous
  - Rotary Club Data, 1934-1935
  - Requests for Photographs, 1932-1933
  - Questionnaire-Class of 1934
  - Relations with Medical School, 1933
  - Requisitions, 1933-1934